DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宮飯》
No way.
不會吧
Falin…
法琳
C-Could she really be resurrected from that condition?
她真的有辦法從那種狀態復活嗎？
It's not unprecedented, but…
雖然也不是沒有前例，但是…
H-Hey, Laios.
喂，萊歐斯
We don't know that yet.
我們還無法確定吧
I'll take her to the resurrection office.
我要帶她去復活處
Are you planning to take the entire mass?
你打算把全部的屍骨都帶過去嗎？
There are probably Warg bones in there as well.
魔狼的骨頭也混在裡面吧
I can't distinguish them, so…
因為我已經沒辦法區分了…
I'll help.
我來幫你
Wait!
等一下！
The bond between her soul and flesh is very fragile right now.
靈魂跟肉體的連結正逐漸減弱
Moving her remains is risky.
隨意搬動她會有很大的風險
The greater the damage to one's flesh, the more likely their soul is to depart.
肉體的缺損越嚴重 靈魂就越有可能分離
The main reason some resurrections fail
復活失敗的大部分原因
is the soul's departure or the incomplete restoration of the body.
不是靈魂已完全分離 就是肉體未修復完整
So, what do we do?
那我們該怎麼做？
Bring a revivifier and resurrect her right here.
把復活屋帶過來，在這裡復活她
But it requires twice the calories of the damaged parts to restore her.
但是修復會需要 缺損部分兩倍以上的卡路里
They'll need to bring a substantial amount of fresh blood and flesh along.
還必須將大量的新鮮血肉一起運過來
-They'll rot on their way here-- -No.
-在路上就會腐壞… -不
What?
什麼？
Yes.
沒錯
We have an abundance of fresh blood and flesh right here.
現在當場就有堆積成山的新鮮血肉
W-Wait a minute!
等等！
Are you going to resurrect her?
你打算復活她嗎？
Using dragon flesh?
而且還是用龍肉？
But resurrection magic isn't your specialty, is it?
復活術並不是你的專長吧？
I've been silent about it because I didn't want to alarm you.
因為怕會嚇到你們 所以我一直不想說
But I specialize in the study of ancient magic that's forbidden now.
其實我的專業領域是 研究在現代被視為禁忌的古代魔法
I think using that is the only way we can bring her back.
我認為現在唯一的辦法 就是以其救活法琳
It's not honest magic, but still.
雖然這不是什麼正派魔法
-What? -Black magic?
-什麼？ -你要用黑魔法？
Don't. No good will come of it.
住手，那不是什麼好東西
There is no good or evil in magic.
魔法才不分善惡
What do you say, Laios?
你要怎麼做？萊歐斯
Do it, Marcille.
拜託你了，瑪露希爾
Bring Falin back to life.
讓法琳活過來吧
Leave it to me.
交給我
I'll try my best.
我試試看
Are you all out of your minds?
你們都瘋了嗎？
You're seriously going to use dragon flesh?
竟然要用龍肉？
Usually, they use goats or pigs.
通常也會用上山羊肉或豬肉
It's kinda late to start having qualms about it.
如今何必糾結在這一點上？
Marcille.
瑪露希爾
Her body should be as close to its original state as possible,
首先我想盡量將她的身體 回復到原本的形狀
so I'll start by reconstructing her bone structure.
所以我要把法琳的骨骼組合起來
I see.
知道了
I have some knowledge of a dog's skeletal framework.
我對於狗的骨骼也略有了解
I'll work on putting together a Warg's frame.
就由我來組合魔狼的骨骼吧
That's not necessary, is it?
不需要那麼做吧！
It could help avoid oversights or errors!
這樣也許能避免遺漏或是錯置啊！
Humans typically have around 200 bones.
人類的骨頭大約有200塊
So, that means there are roughly 840 bones here.
那現在這裡大約有840塊骨頭
Huh? That many?
什麼？有那麼多嗎？
Based on the skulls, there were two Wargs.
從頭骨看來，應該有兩隻魔狼
A dog's body has around 320 bones.
狗的骨頭數量大約是320塊左右
It should be easier if we begin with the simpler bones.
先從明顯看得出來的部分開始就行了
The more rounded one is a human rib cage.
較接近圓弧狀的是人類的肋骨
Next, the vertebrae that connect with the ribs.
接下來是連接肋骨的脊椎
This is easy as well since the curvature of the spine is so distinct.
由於兩者彎曲程度完全不同 所以也很容易分辨
The tricky part is the smaller bones of the arms and legs.
問題就在手跟腳的細小骨頭
I can't distinguish them at all.
完全無法區分這部分的骨頭
Let's start sorting them out, beginning with the prominent ones.
就從最顯眼的開始排列吧
The largest bone here is the ankle bone.
這一塊最大的是踝骨
Arrange the other large bones in a way that fits,
然後照順序 把第二大的骨頭依形狀拼湊
and we have the instep of a foot.
就組完腳背骨了
Lastly, the bones of the hand.
接下來就剩下手骨
Let's start by arranging the fingers.
就從手指開始排列好了
I got it!
我看出來了！
Like this, right?
是這樣排列，對吧？
Close!
差一點！
The longest metacarpal isn't in the middle finger
掌骨最長的不是中指
but in the index finger.
而是食指
Finally, we need to find the carpal bones that connect the fingers to her arm.
最後就只剩下連接手指跟手臂的腕骨
Give me a hint!
給我提示！
You better not be enjoying this!
不要樂在其中啦！
There.
好了
It's done!
完成！
THE BONE STRUCTURES OF FALIN AND WARGS
（法琳與魔狼的骨骼結構）
I don't know how to put it, but…
雖然不知道該怎麼形容這心情…
they're such beautiful skeletal frameworks.
不過這真是一具漂亮的骨骼
They're really nice skeletons now.
骨頭長得很好
It seems they had good calcium.
看來有攝取足夠的鈣質
This won't revive the Wargs as well, will it?
魔狼不會也一起復活吧？
The only souls confined to the dungeon are those of humans.
只有人類的靈魂會被束縛在迷宮中
Otherwise, this place would be crowded with the souls of all sorts of creatures.
不然迷宮早就被 各種生物的靈魂塞爆了
Well then, I'll start.
那麼，我要開始了
O Pilitsham.
歐皮力茲薩姆
O Esdoms. O Villaru.
歐艾斯都姆斯，歐碧拉爾
Casuszameo Rotokt Artumcuks.
凱斯札梅歐洛托科托阿拓姆庫庫斯
O Kunquikeo. Eoktum Kome.
歐昆奇凱歐艾歐科特姆可梅
Tumao Elm Finktow Kemesfo. Aoewauk Aentujon.
特瑪歐艾爾姆芬科托凱梅斯佛 阿歐艾娃烏科阿安特鍾
Aoewauk Aentujon…
阿歐艾娃烏科阿安特鍾…
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
She's unconscious.
她昏過去了
What happened?
情況如何？
Did it work?
成功了嗎？
Falin!
法琳！
Her air passage is blocked with blood.
有血積在她的呼吸道裡
Try to stay calm and spit it out.
冷靜地把血吐出來
You're safe now.
你已經沒事了
Falin.
法琳
Laios…
哥哥…
Thank goodness.
太好了
Cold…
好冰…
Right, my armor!
也是啦，鎧甲很冰涼吧！
Sorry! I'll get you something to wear!
抱歉！我去拿衣服給你穿！
Falin, are you okay?
法琳，你還好嗎？
Are you unhurt?
有沒有哪裡會痛？
That's good.
那就好
Marcille.
瑪露希爾
Marcille!
瑪露希爾！
What happened to Falin?
法琳怎麼樣了？
She's come back to life.
她復活了
She still seems a bit disoriented, though.
雖然她的腦袋感覺還有一點混亂
Falin!
法琳！
Thank goodness!
謝天謝地！
I'm so relieved!
真的太好了！
Marcille…
瑪露希爾…
Chil…
奇爾…
How's she doing?
她還好嗎？
She still seems to be a little confused.
她好像還搞不太清楚狀況
Right. Let me introduce him.
對了，我介紹一下
This is Senshi.
這傢伙是先西
He helped us a lot on our journey.
一路上他幫了我們很多
Hello, Falin.
幸會啊，法琳
It's nice to meet you.
很高興能見到你
Sen…
先…
Let's start preparing our meal!
我們開始準備做飯吧！
Thank goodness!
太好了…
I'm so relieved!
我這下放心啦！
M-Marcille.
瑪露希爾
I can wash myself, you know.
我自己會洗啦
I had to make sure your skin was restored properly.
我得確認一下你的皮膚 有沒有好好恢復啊
It tickles!
好癢喔！
You have a bruise here!
這裡竟然有瘀血！
T-That's from when I tripped
這是我小時候跌倒
and bumped my chin on the edge of the steps as a kid.
撞到樓梯角留下的啦
Oh.
什麼嘛
Marcille, you look paler than me.
我覺得你的臉色還比較差
I'm just running low on magic.
只是魔力耗盡而已啦
I'll be fine if I have something to eat and rest a little…
待會吃了飯，好好休息一下就沒事…
What are you doing?
你幹嘛？
I just wanted to share some of my magic with you.
只是想把我的魔力分一點給你
Oh, please.
你也真是的
You don't have enough magic right now to share.
你現在的魔力還沒多到能分給別人吧
But I do.
不
I'm feeling surprisingly great.
我現在狀態絕佳
There's this power welling up inside me.
不斷有力量湧現
But it's a bit like recovering from an illness,
但是你現在就像是病剛治好的狀態
so hold off on using magic until you're back on your feet, okay?
在身體適應之前，就不要使用魔力了
I died, didn't I?
我曾死過一次對吧？
I can't remember how it happened.
當時的事情我想不太起來
What exactly happened?
到底發生了什麼事？
Everyone is exhausted and scarred.
大家都遍體鱗傷
And why is the Red Dragon here?
炎龍怎麼會出現在這種地方？
Are Namari and Shuro safe?
娜瑪莉和修洛沒事吧？
If everyone had to push themselves because of me, then…
如果因為我而勉強到大家…
That's not…
沒有那回事…
And what's up with that magic circle?
而且那個魔法陣是怎麼回事？
It didn't look like anything good.
看起來不是什麼好東西
If I forced you to use something like that…
難道是我逼你用了那種魔法陣…
It's fine!
沒事的！
Sure, getting here was challenging, and I had some rough times.
雖然一路走來很辛苦 也吃了不少苦頭
But now, they're all just stories to laugh about
不過如今都變成能笑著談論的往事了
because everything worked out!
因為一切都順利成功啦！
So, don't worry about it.
所以你別再像這樣感到不安了
None of us has any regrets at all.
沒有任何一個人感到後悔
We can erase that magic circle altogether, and it will be fine.
大家待會一起 消除那個魔法陣就沒問題了
For now…
目前啊…
our main concern is the journey back.
我最擔心的是要怎麼回去
What should we do about your clothes?
你的替換衣物該怎麼辦？
And I have to wash and dry mine.
我的衣服也得洗了再弄乾
Honestly, if it weren't for those frogs…
真是的，只要沒有那隻青蛙…
Frogs?
青蛙？
What's the plan now?
接下來要怎麼做？
Head back to the surface.
我們回到地表吧
We can't use return magic or the Orcs' secret passage anymore.
回歸魔法以及 半獸人的祕密通道已經不能用了
We'll have to take the main road back to the castle.
我們得走大路回城堡才行
That's not what I meant.
我不是那個意思
Even though you've rescued your sister, you're still penniless.
就算你救了妹妹 但你還是身無分文啊
I do have some savings in the bank.
我在銀行裡還有一點存款啦
But you don't have a token, right?
不過你沒有領款票據吧？
And to get it reissued, it'll take a month.
申請補發需要一個月
That's the predicament.
的確是那樣啦
Anyway, Marcille, that girl!
話說回來，瑪露希爾那傢伙真是的！
Did you know, Laios?
你之前知情嗎？萊歐斯
That she could use black magic?
她竟會用黑魔法
She never shared many details,
我沒有詳細聽她說過
but she mentioned wanting to explore the dungeon for her studies.
但她有說是為了研究才想來探索迷宮
I thought it was odd.
我一直都覺得奇怪
Why would an elf who doesn't seem to be desperate venture into the dungeon?
看起來衣食無虞的精靈 竟然主動進迷宮？
She's not one of those dark elves, is she?
那傢伙該不會是黑暗精靈吧？
I hope this won't lead to any trouble.
希望不要發展成什麼麻煩事
Who are you calling a dark elf?
你說誰是黑暗精靈？
I-I mean, if it was harmless, it wouldn't be forbidden, right?
因為如果那是無害的 就不會變成禁忌了吧？
Harmless?
無害？
Even recovery magic can be used for torture.
就連治癒魔法都能用在拷問上
Just like a blade, it depends on how you use it.
跟一把利刃相同 就看你怎麼使用而已
I study forbidden arts to benefit people.
我研究禁術是想為人們做出貢獻
I have nothing to feel guilty about.
我問心無愧喔
But concerning the method of resurrection I used,
不過關於這次復活的方法
it's best for all of us to forget about it.
我們彼此都忘了比較好，拜託了
So you do feel guilty about it!
那你就是心中有愧嘛！
Oh, well. Never mind.
算了，隨便啦
It's all in the past now.
事情都過去了
By the way…
話說回來…
Where's Senshi?
先西去哪了？
Preparing the dragon meat, I imagine.
應該是去處理龍肉
I just passed Mr. Senshi carrying a pot and some firewood.
拿著鍋子跟柴火的先西先生 剛才和我擦身而過
What did I tell you?
看吧
He's getting ready to cook.
他在準備料理
Cook…
料理…
Near the dragon?
在龍的旁邊？
-This is bad!
-完蛋了！
What's wrong?
到底怎麼了？
When we opened up the dragon, we opened its fuel bag, too.
我們剖開龍的時候也把燃料袋打開了
If he starts a fire there now…
要是他現在在那裡點火…
Senshi!
先西！
Stop!
住手！
W-We're alive.
我們還活著耶
Is this defense magic?
這是防禦魔法？
Falin, did you do this?
法琳，是你做的嗎？
It seems so.
好像是耶
In that split second?
就在那一瞬間？
Without chanting?
甚至沒有詠唱？
I don't know.
我不清楚
I just felt I had to protect everyone and…
在剛才那瞬間 我一心想著要保護大家…
That's amazing.
真厲害
Kind of like an adrenaline rush, huh?
就像是危機時刻 腎上腺素激發出的力量？
If only we had that power during the fight with the Red Dragon.
在我們跟炎龍的戰鬥中 如果有這股力量就方便多了
A-Anyway, you've just been revived,
總之你才剛復活不久
so hold off on using any more magic, okay?
就盡量不要再用魔力了
That took me by surprise.
真的嚇了一大跳
I told you dragons breathe fire with their self-made fuel, right?
我之前跟你說過 龍是用自製的燃料噴火不是嗎？
Your fire ignited that fuel.
你點著了那燃料
It won't go out.
火完全不會滅呢
The fat in its body is burning.
看來是牠體內的脂肪在燃燒
It'll eventually go out.
遲早會熄滅的
Until then, I won't be able to get its meat.
裡面的肉到火熄滅前都拿不出來了
What a pickle.
讓人頭痛
Maybe I could use that for cooking.
就用這個來做飯吧
Combine flour, yeast, salt, and water, and knead well.
將麵粉、酵母、鹽和水 攪拌均勻後揉成麵團
Let it rest for a while and…
靜置一段時間…
In the meantime, go take a bath.
這段時間去洗澡吧
Stretch and shape the dough,
將麵團攤開並調整形狀
then add toppings to it.
在麵皮上鋪滿料
Sprinkle flour on the dragon's skin,
在龍皮上撒上少量的麵粉
then, put them inside the dragon.
放進龍的體內
Cut off the tip of the tail.
切下龍尾尖端
What a waste!
好浪費啊！
Peel the skin and use it to make a soup.
剝皮後放入湯中
Cut the meat into blocks and sear on the hot dragon scales until golden.
把肉成塊切下 放到加熱後的龍鱗上烤至上色
Then, marinate in sauce.
然後浸到調味料中
It's done!
完成啦！
DRAGON TAIL SOUP
（龍尾湯）
ONION PIZZA, ROAST RED DRAGON
（洋蔥披薩，烤炎龍肉）
Looks so good!
看起來好好吃！
Can we eat it?
我們可以吃了嗎？
-Of course, not!
-當然不行啊！
It's delicious!
真美味！
It feels like the first meal I had in a long time.
感覺這是我隔很久第一次吃東西
Good!
很好！
It's your turn to eat your fill of it.
那就好好吃個夠吧
Oh, well.
算了，她喜歡就好
She seems to be enjoying it, so.
看起來也一副朝氣蓬勃的樣子
It's really chewy, but the taste is oddly familiar.
肉質超硬，但卻是讓人熟悉的味道
What is this taste?
這到底是什麼味道啊？
It's not quite like beef or pork, though.
既不像牛肉，也不像豬肉
And this flavor reminds me…
而且感覺這風味…
a little of Living Armor, don't you think?
不覺得有點像是會動的鎧甲嗎？
Does it?
是嗎？
It doesn't have that rusty smell, though.
跟那種鐵鏽味不太一樣吧
And the Kelpie and frog meat were more tender.
水棲馬和大青蛙的肉就很軟
If anything, it's a bit like the Basilisk.
跟巴西利斯克比較相似吧
What do you think, Laios?
你覺得呢？萊歐斯
I don't know what you're all on about.
你們都在胡說什麼啊？
This vibrant red!
這鮮紅的顏色！
This firmness!
紮實的口感！
This rich taste!
濃郁的味道！
Each characteristic is like no other!
不管在哪一方面都是絕無僅有！
Why compare the taste of dragon with other creatures in the first place?
而且說到底為什麼要以其他生物 來形容龍的味道？
This is the taste of a dragon!
這就是龍獨特的味道啊！
Um, Falin.
那個，法琳啊
You might have already figured this out, but…
我想你應該已經多多少少察覺到了…
We couldn't afford to buy food, so we made it this far by eating monsters.
因為我們買不起食物 所以一路上都是靠吃魔物維生
That's amazing.
太棒了
That's amazing!
太棒了…
What monsters did you eat?
你們吃過什麼魔物？
H-How did you prepare them?
是怎麼吃的呢？
Seems like we didn't have to worry.
看來是我們杞人憂天
This is exactly what I was afraid of!
我就是害怕會演變成這樣啊！
First, we had a Huge Scorpion and a Slime.
我們剛開始吃了大蠍子跟史萊姆
We even tried a Walking Mushroom.
還吃了走路菇喔
A Walking Mushroom?
走路菇？
We even harvested vegetables from Golems.
我們還曾經從巨魔像上收割過蔬菜
What about a Fish-man?
魚人呢？
We didn't try that.
我們沒吃魚人
But we did eat Living Armor.
不過有吃過會動的鎧甲喔
What?! What part did you eat?
真的嗎？是吃哪一個部位？
Um, it's actually a colony of mollusks wearing a shell and…
那其實是包著殼的軟體動物群…
Wouldn't it be simpler to just show her the real thing?
直接給她看實物不是更快嗎？
What's this?
這是怎樣？
Why didn't you tell us about it?!
為什麼？你為何瞞著我們啊？
Sorry.
對不起啦
It's cute. Is it a pulmonata?
好可愛喔，是有肺類嗎？
It went back inside.
縮回去了
It moves on its own.
這傢伙會隨意亂動
Seriously?
真的假的？
My bad.
抱歉
I planned to keep it temporarily until I found another weapon at first.
我本來是打算暫時拿來頂替 直到找到其他武器為止
But I kept it because of its useful reactions to other monsters.
不過因為這把劍 感知其他魔物的能力實在太方便了
So that's how you showed really sharp instincts now and then!
現在回想起來 你有時的確敏銳得嚇人！
We should've gotten Namari to examine it.
那時候應該讓娜瑪莉鑑定一下
In that situation, I agree you had no choice but to use the sword.
在那樣的情況下 我也認為你只能使用那把劍
But it shouldn't have been a solo decision.
但你不能擅自決定啊
The greatest damage is the loss of trust from your teammates.
失去周遭的信任會是你最大的損失
It was careless of me.
我太輕率了
It won't happen again.
不會再做這種事了
So, what will you do with it?
所以你打算怎麼處理那把劍？
Until I find another weapon, I'd like to keep using it.
在找到其他武器之前 希望你們能讓我繼續使用
I could dunk it in water and drown the creature.
我可以讓劍沉入水中，溺死魔物
I'd have to disassemble the sword to remove it,
不將劍拆解開來就無法把魔物取出
so it'll probably rot inside, though.
所以到時會在劍中腐壞吧
That's kinda unpleasant.
感覺好不舒服
I suppose we can wait and see for a while.
我們先暫時觀望一下好了
You're the one who said monsters are dangerous.
當初明明就是你說魔物很危險
It's not like I forgot about that.
我並沒有忘記自己說過的話
But I thought I had neutralized it
但我以為已經讓這魔物失去力量了
and that I could use it to my advantage.
想說這樣也許就能利用這份能力
But it didn't pan out.
不過果然還是不行
I guess it's impossible to use a monster while keeping it alive.
活著的魔物還是不可能為人所用
What does it taste like?
吃起來是什麼味道？
Wanna try?
你想吃吃看嗎？
Oh, yeah!
我想吃…
There are a lot of doors, but only two of them lead outside.
雖然到處都是門 但只有兩道能通到外面
No need to worry about surprise attacks, then.
看來不太需要擔心會被人突襲
This house seems quite comfortable.
這房子感覺住起來會很舒服
The fact it has seven toilets raises questions, though.
有七間廁所這件事讓我有點在意
All right. Let's get some sleep here.
好，我們就在這邊補眠吧
Hurray!
萬歲！
It's been so long since I last slept on a bed!
能久違地躺在床上睡覺啦！
We'll still have to use our sleeping bags as blankets, though.
但棉被還是跟平常一樣是睡袋啦
Sorry for intruding on your home without asking.
抱歉我們擅自進來打擾
We'll leave as soon as we rest a little.
我們休息一下就會馬上離開
What's the matter?
怎麼了？
I think she's a resident.
好像是這裡的居民
She says she'll let us stay.
她說我們可以住下來
I see.
這樣啊
That's great.
真是感謝她
We're short on sleeping bags, so we'll have to share on the way back.
因為睡袋不夠 回程我們都得貼在一起睡喔
We haven't slept in the same bed since our school days!
上次在同一張床睡覺 是在學生時期吧！
I wonder if we'll both fit.
塞得進我們兩個嗎？
I've gotten much bigger since then.
我跟那個時候相比，變大了很多
You cheeky little!
說什麼大話啊？
To me, you'll always be my little girl!
你在我的心中一直都還是小女孩啊！
I'm really glad I got to see you again.
我真的很高興能再見到你
Me, too.
我也是
I'll go say goodnight to my brother before bed.
睡前我想去跟哥哥打聲招呼
Laios.
哥哥
Falin.
法琳
This scar…
這傷口…
You did something reckless, didn't you?
你一定做了什麼莽撞的事吧？
Why did you…
為什麼要…
Just to be clear, you're the one who did something reckless first.
我跟你說清楚，先亂來的可是你
So it's on you that things turned out like this!
都是因為你才變成這樣！
What?
什麼？
Don't ever do something like that again!
不准再做那種傻事了！
I can't even recall what I did.
我根本不記得自己做了什麼
I won't do it again.
我答應你不會再做了
Goodnight, Laios.
晚安，萊歐斯哥哥
Goodnight, Falin.
晚安，法琳
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：黃可涵